In October 2010,
في اكتوبر 2010
the Justice League of America will be teaming up with The 99.
سيتحد ابطال العدالة بأمريكا مع الـ99
Icons like Batman,
رموز مثل الرجل الوطواط
Superman, Wonder Woman and their colleagues
وسوبر مان و المرأة الخارقة ورفاقهم سوف يتحدون جنباً الى جنب
will be teaming up with icons Jabbar, Noora,
مع رموز مثل جبار .. نورا
Jami and their colleagues.
جامع .. و رفاقهم
It's a story of intercultural intersections,
انها قصة عن تواصل بيني للحضارات
and what better group
ويالها من مجموعة
to have this conversation
ستقوم بهذا الحوار
than those that grew out of fighting fascism
بدلا من تلك المجموعات التي خرجت جراء محاربة الفاشية
in their respective histories and geographies?
والتي لها مفاهيمها الثقافية والجغرافية الخاصة بها
As fascism took over Europe in the 1930s,
عندما استولت الفاشية على اوروبا في الثلاثينات
an unlikely reaction came out of North America.
ظهرت حركة مقاومة خاصة في شمال امريكا
As Christian iconography got changed,
حيث تم تحوير بعض السمات المسيحية
and swastikas were created out of crucifixes,
تشابه إستخدام النازيين للصليب المعكوف رمزا لهم .. مستمد من صلب المسيح
Batman and Superman were created by Jewish young men
الرجل الوطواط و سوبر مان .. شخصيات صنعها شبان يهود
in the United States and Canada,
في الولايات المتحدة وكندا
also going back to the Bible.
معتمدين على نصوص وردت في الانجيل
Consider this:
فكرو فيما سأقول .!
like the prophets, all the superheroes
فمثل جميع الانبياء .. كان الابطال الخارقون
are missing parents.
يتامى
Superman's parents die on Krypton
فوالدا سوبر مان .. توفي على كوكب كريبتون
before the age of one.
قبل ان يطال السنة الاولى من عمره
Bruce Wayne, who becomes Batman,
و بروس وين الذي اصبح الرجل الوطواط
loses his parents at the age of six in Gotham City.
فقد والديه عندما كان في السادسة من عمره في مدينة " جوثهام "
Spiderman is raised
وقد تربى الرجل العنكبوت
by his aunt and uncle.
على يد عمته وعمه
And all of them, just like the prophets who get their message
وجميعهم ..وكما الانبياء الذين تلقوا رسالتهم
from God through Gabriel,
من الله عبر الملاك جبريل ..
get their message from above.
فقد تلقوا رسائلهم من السماء
Peter Parker is in a library in Manhattan
فبيتر باركر عندما كان في المكتبة في مانهاتن
when the spider descends from above
هبط عليه عنكبوت من الاعلى
and gives him his message through a bite.
لكي يعطيه رسالته عبر " عضة "
Bruce Wayne is in his bedroom
وبروس وين الذي كان في غرفة نومه
when a big bat flies over his head,
طار فوق راسه وطواط
and he sees it as an omen to become Batman.
فتكهن انه سيغدو الرجل الوطواط
Superman is not only sent to Earth
سوبر مان لم يرسل فقط الى الارض
from the heavens, or Krypton,
من السماء .. او من كوكب كريبتون
but he's sent in a pod, much like Moses was on the Nile.
ولكنه ارسل ضمن مركبة فضائية .. كما ارسل موسى عبر النيل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you hear the voice of his father, Jor-El,
وسمع صوت والده .. جور-ال
saying to Earth, "I have sent to you my only son."
يقول له عندما وصل الى الارض " يا بني الوحيد لقد ارسلتك الى الارض "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
These are clearly biblical archetypes,
اذا هنالك جذور انجيلية في تلك القصص
and the thinking behind that was to create
والفكر كانت في صنع
positive, globally-resonating storylines
نسق إيجابي لقصص عالمية
that could be tied to the same things
لتربط الاشياء نفسها التي
that other people were pulling mean messages out of
يستخدمها البعض في أستنباط معاني سيئة
because then the person that's using religion for the wrong purpose
بسبب الأشخاص الذين يستخدمون الدين لأسباب خاطئة
just becomes a bad man with a bad message.
فقط يصبحون رجال أشرار يحملون رسالة سيئة
And it's only by linking positive things
وفقط بواسطة التفكير الايجابي في الأشياء
that the negative can be delinked.
يمكن ان نطغى على التفكير السلبي المرتبط بها
This is the kind of thinking that went into
وهذا النوع من التفكير الذي أستغرقنا فيه
creating The 99.
لصناعة الابطال الـ 99
The 99 references the 99 attributes of Allah in the Koran,
فالابطال الـ 99 ، مرجعها اسماء الله الحسنى في القران
things like generosity and mercy and foresight and wisdom
مثل الكرم والرحمة والسماح والحكمة
and dozens of others that no two people in the world would disagree about.
ودرازن غيرها من الاسماء التي لا يختلف عليها اثنين في العالم
It doesn't matter what your religion is;
مهما كانت ديانته
even if you're an atheist, you don't raise your kid telling him, you know,
وحتى لو كان ملحدا .. فلا اعتقد ان الملحد سوف يربي اولاده
"Make sure you lie three times a day."
على وجوب الكذب ثلاث مرات يوميا
Those are basic human values.
لان هذه مفاهيم واخلاق إنسانية عامة
And so the backstory of The 99
وترجع قصة الابطال الـ 99
takes place in 1258,
حيث تبدأ في عام 1258
which history tells us the Mongols invaded Baghdad and destroyed it.
حسب التاريخ ، عندما اجتاح المغول بغداد ودمروها
All the books from Bait al-Hikma library,
كل الكتب الموجودة في مكتبة دار الحكمة
the most famous library in its day, were thrown in the Tigris River,
أشهر مكتبة في عصرها ، حيث رميت في نهر دجلة
and the Tigris changes color with ink.
حتى تغير لون النهر الى لون الحبر
It's a story passed on generation after generation.
وهي قصة متواترة جيلا بعد جيل
I rewrote that story,
وقد أعدت كتابة تلك القصة
and in my version, the librarians find out that this is going to happen --
و في روايتي ..علم القائمون على المكتبة أن هذا سيحدث
and here's a side note:
وهذه ملاحظة جانبية :
if you want a comic book to do well, make the librarians the hero. It always works well.
أذا أردت لمجموعه قصصية أن تباع جيداً ، أجعل القائمون على المكتبة هم الأبطال ، دائما تنجح هذه الحيلة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So the librarians find out
اذا القائمون على المكتبة إكتشفوا ذلك
and they get together a special solution, a chemical solution called King's Water,
وأجتمعوا لكي يخرجوا بحل خاص بتلك الازمة .. وقد كان الحل كيميائي يدعى " ماء الملك "
that when mixed with 99 stones
يتم خلطه مع 99 حجراً
would be able to save all that culture and history in the books.
مما يؤدي الى حفظ كل المعلومات والعلوم الموجودة في الكتب
But the Mongols get there first.
ولكن المغول وصلوا اليهم قبل ان يتموا مهمتهم
The books and the solution get thrown in the Tigris River.
لذا فقد تم رمي الكتب .. وذلك الحل الكيميائي الى نهر دجلة
Some librarians escape, and over the course of days and weeks,
وقد استطاع بعض من القائمين على المكتبة من الهروب .. وقد كانوا على مدى اسابيع
they dip the stones into the Tigris and suck up that collective wisdom
يرمون احجاراً الى قاع نهر دجلة ومن ثم يعيدون سحبها .. لكي يجمعوا المعلومات وافكار الكتب
that we all think is lost to civilization.
والتي ظن الناس انها فقدت الى الابد
Those stones have been smuggled as three prayer beads
وقد تم تهريب هذه الاحجار عبر ثلاث قوافل
of 33 stones each
كل قافلة تحوي 33 حجرا
through Arabia into Andalusia in Spain, where they're safe for 200 years.
عبر الصحراء العربية الى الاندلس حيث تم حفظها لمدة 200 عام
But in 1492, two important things happen.
ولكن في عام 1942 حدث امرين مهمين
The first is the fall of Granada,
الاول سقوط غرناطة
the last Muslim enclave in Europe.
المعقل الاخير للمسلمين في اوروبا
The second is Columbus finally gets funded to go to India, but he gets lost.
والثاني هو اكتشاف كريستوفر كلومبس امريكا بدلا من الهند عندما اضاع الطريق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So 33 of the stones are smuggled
لذا تم تهريب الاحجار على ثلاث دفعات ال 33 حجر الاولى
onto the Nina, the Pinta and the Santa Maria
تم نقلها الى نينا ..ومن ثم بينيتا .. ومن ثم سانتا ماريا
and are spread in the New World.
ومن ثم انتشرت في العالم الحديث
Thirty-three go on the Silk Road to China, South Asia and Southeast Asia.
وقد ذهبت ال33 حجر الثانية الى الصين عبر طريق الحرير والى جنوب اسيا وجنوب شرقها
And 33 are spread between Europe, the Middle East and Africa.
وال33 الاخيرة تم نشرها في اوروبا والشرق الاوسط وافريقا
And now it's 2010, and there are 99 heroes
والان وفي عام 2010 خرج الابطال ال99
from 99 different countries.
من 99 بلداً
Now it's very easy to assume
الآن من السهل التخمين
that those books, because they were from a library called Bait al-Hikma, were Muslim books,
أن تلك الكتب ، ولأنها من مكتبة تدعي الحكمة ، أنها كتب إسلامية
but that's not the case because the caliph that built that library,
ولكن هذا خطا شائع ، لأن الخليفة الذي بنى هذه المكتبة
his name was al-Ma'mun -- he was Harun al-Rashid's son.
إسمه المأمون ..وهو ابن هارون الرشيد
He had told his advisers, "Get me all the scholars
والذي قال لمستشاريه ..اجمعوا لي كل العلماء
to translate any book they can get their hands onto into Arabic,
وقولوا لهم ان كل من يترجم كتابا الى العربية
and I will pay them its weight in gold."
سوف اعطيه وزنه ذهباً
After a while, his advisers complained.
وبعد حين تذمر المستشارين
They said, "Your Highness, the scholars are cheating.
وقالوا للخليفة " مولانا .. ان العلماء يغشون
They're writing in big handwriting to take more gold."
انهم يكتبون بخط كبير لكي يحصلوا على صفحات اكثر.. وبالتالي ذهب اكثر "
To which he said, "Let them be, because what they're giving us
فقال لهم " دعهم يفعلون ما يريدون فما نأخذه منهم ...
is worth a lot more than what we're paying them."
اكثر بكثير مما نعطيهم اياه "
So the idea of an open architecture, an open knowledge,
إذا فكرة مفتوح المصدر ، و المعرفة الحرة
is not new to my neck of the desert.
ليس امراً جديد علي انا ابن الصحراء
The concept centers on something called the Noor stones.
ومفهوم القصة يتركز على احجار تدعى "احجار النور"
Noor is Arabic for light.
ونور تعني بالعربية " الضوء "
So these 99 stones, a few kind of rules in the game:
وهنالك بضع اساسيات للعبة "احجار النور"
Number one, you don't choose the stone; the stone chooses you.
الاولى ان الحجر هو الذي يختارك ولست انت من يختاره
There's a King Arthur element to the storyline, okay.
اي هنالك تشابه مع قصة الملك آرثر
Number two, all of The 99,
والثاني هو ان جميع الابطال الـ 99
when they first get their stone, or their power, abuse it;
عندما يحصلون على قوتهم في البداية يسيئون استخدامها
they use it for self-interest.
ويستخدمونها لمصالحهم الشخصية
And there's a very strong message in there that when you start abusing your stone,
وهنالك رسالة قوية من اساءة استخدام قوتك
you get taken advantage of
حيث في هذا النسق سوف يستغلك
by people who will exploit your powers, okay.
اشخاص سيئون لكي يفسدون تلك القوة التي تملك ويستخدمونها لاغراض شريرة
Number three, the 99 stones all have within them
الامر الثالث هو ان الاحجار ال99 ، كلها بداخلها
a mechanism that self-updates.
نظام خاص لتحديثها
Now there are two groups that exist within the Muslim world.
والآن هنالك في العالم الاسلامي نوعان من الاشخاص
Everybody believes the Koran is for all time and all place.
الكل يؤمن بان القرآن صالح لكل زمان و مكان
Some believe that means that the original interpretation
البعض يؤمن بأن معاني والتفسير الأصلي
from a couple thousand years ago is what's relevant today.
حيث ظهر منذ الفي عام وهو ليس ملائم لحالنا اليوم
I don't belong there.
أنا لا أتبع هذا الإعتقاد
Then there's a group that believes the Koran is a living, breathing document,
وهنالك من يؤمن ان القران هو كتاب حي ، يعيش و يتنفس
and I captured that idea within these stones that self-update.
وقد اخذت هذه الفكرة وادرجتها في احجار النور
Now the main bad guy, Rughal,
الان الشخصية الرئيسية السيئة في هذه القصة هو " راجال "
does not want these stones to update,
لا يريد لهذه الاحجار أن تحدث نفسها
so he's trying to get them to stop updating.
لذا سيحاول أن يجعل الأبطال يوقفو تحديثها
He can't use the stones, but he can stop them.
وهو لايستطيع استخدام هذه الاحجار ولكنه يستطيع وقفها
And by stopping them, he has more of a fascist agenda,
وبايقافها ... سيستطيع ان يتم اجندته الشريرة
where he gets some of The 99 to work for him --
حيث سيستخدم بعضا من الابطال الـ 99
they're all wearing cookie-cutter, same color uniforms
وكلهم يلبسون نفس الزي وبنفس الألوان
They're not allowed to individually express who they are and what they are.
ولا يحق لهم كأفراد التعبير عن أنفسهم أو ماهيتهم
And he controls them from the top down --
وهو يتحكم فيهم من الأعلى إلى الأسفل
whereas when they work for the other side, eventually,
وعندما سيتم تحريرهم لكي يعملوا مع الطرف الاخر
when they find out this is the wrong person, they've been manipulated,
عندما يكتشفون انهم كانوا يعملون مع الطرف الخاطىء وانه تم خداعهم
they actually, each one has a different, colorful
في الحقيقة ، كل واحد منهم له لون
kind of dress.
رداء خاص به
And the last point about the 99 Noor stones is this.
والنقطة الاخيرة عن الـ 99 حجرا
So The 99 work in teams of three.
هي ان الابطال الـ 99 يعملون ضمن فرق مكونة من 3 أعضاء
Why three? A couple of reasons.
لماذا ثلاثة ؟ لسببين
Number one, we have a thing within Islam that you don't leave a boy and a girl alone together,
الاول لدينا شيء في الاسلام يقول " ما اختلا رجلٌ بإمراة .....
because the third person is temptation or the devil, right?
الا وكان الشيطان ثالثهما "
I think that's there in all cultures, right?
وهذا موجود في جميع الثقافات اليس كذلك ؟
But this is not about religion, it's not about proselytizing.
وهذا لا يتعلق بالاديان ولا بالروحانيات
There's this very strong social message
انما هنالك رسالة اجتماعية قوية من ورائها
that needs to get to kind of
تنص على وجوب
the deepest crevices of intolerance,
تلافي كل التعصبات الموجودة اليوم
and the only way to get there is to kind of play the game.
والطريقة الوحيدة للوصول لذلك هي عبر لعب هذه اللعبة
And so this is the way I dealt with it.
وهذه هي الطريقة التي تعاملت بها معها
They work in teams of three: two boys and a girl, two girls and a boy,
ويعملون في فرق ثلاثية إما ذكرين وانثى .. او ذكر و انثتين
three boys, three girls, no problem.
او ثلاثة ذكور ، ثلاث اناث ، لا مشكلة
And the Swiss psychoanalyst, Carl Jung, also spoke about
بالاضافة الى ان العالم النفسي السويسري " كارل يانج " تحدث عن
the importance of the number three in all cultures, so I figure I'm covered.
أهمية الرقم 3 في جميع الثقافات ، لذا أدركت أنني مدعوم علمياً
Well ...
حسنا ..
I got accused in a few blogs that I was actually sent by the Pope
لقد تم اتهامي في بعض المدونات انني عميل " للبابا"
to preach the Trinity and Catholicism in the Middle East,
واريد ان اسوق لتثليث و للفكر الثالوثي في الشرق الاوسط
so you -- (Laughter)
اذا (: ضحك :)
you believe who you want. I gave you my version of the story.
أعتقدو ما تريدون ، ولكن أنا أعطيكم نسختي من القصة
So here's some of the characters that we have.
وهذه بعض من الشخصيات التي لدينا
Mujiba, from Malaysia: her main power is she's able to answer any question.
مجيبة من ماليزيا .. وقوتها الاساسية هي المعرفة .. فهي قادرة على الاجابة على اي سؤال
She's the Trivial Pursuit queen, if you want,
هي ملكة الاسئلة ان اردتم
but when she first gets her power,
وعندما حصلت على قوتها اول مرة
she starts going on game shows and making money.
استخدمتها للربح في برامج المسابقات لكي تجمع المال
We have Jabbar from Saudi who starts breaking things when he has the power.
ولدينا هنا " جبار " من السعودية ولديه القدرة على تحطيم الاشياء
Now, Mumita was a fun one to name. Mumita is the destroyer.
وهنا "مميته" التي كان من الممتع تسميتها حيث مميتة تعني المدمرة
So the 99 attributes of Allah have the yin and the yang;
ان جميع الاسماء ال99 لها جانبي الين و اليان (الخير و الشر)
there's the powerful, the hegemonous, the strong,
فهناك القوي ، المتين ، العظيم
and there's also the kind, the generous.
وهنالك الرحمن الكريم
I'm like, are all the girls going to be kind and merciful and the guys all strong?
كما ان ليس جميعالأبطال الإناث رحيمات عطوفات ..و ان الذكور هم الأقوياء
I'm like, you know what, I've met a few girls who were destroyers in my lifetime, so ...
فكرت تعرفون ماذا ، لقد قابلت بعض البنات المدمرات عبر حياتي ، لذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We have Jami from Hungary, who first starts making weapons:
ولدينا "جامع" والذي يبدا في مشوراه بتصنيع الاسلحة
He's the technology wiz.
فهو خبير تقني
Musawwira from Ghana,
ولدينا مصورة من غانا
Hadya from Pakistan, Jaleel from Iran who uses fire.
وهادية من باكستان وجليل من ايران وهو نافث نيران
And this is one of my favorites, Al-Batina from Yemen.
وهذه هي بطلتي المفضلة " باطنة " من اليمن
Al-Batina is the hidden.
والباطن هو المخفي
So Al-Batina is hidden, but she's a superhero.
لذا باطنة هي فتاة متخفية ..ولكنها إحدى الأبطال الخارقون
I came home to my wife and I said, "I created a character after you."
وقد رجعت للبيت لأخبر زوجتي أنني صنعت شخصية تشبهك
My wife is a Saudi from Yemeni roots.
زوجتي سعودية من اصول يمنية
And she said, "Show me." So I showed this.
قالت لي " ارني اياها " لذا أريتها هذه
She said, "That's not me."
فقالت " هذه ليست انا "
I said, "Look at the eyes. They're your eyes."
قلت " انظري الى العينين .. انها عيناكي "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I promised my investors this would not be another made-in-fifth-world-country production.
ولقد وعدت المستثمرين ان هذه السلسلة لن تكون مجرد سلسلة هزيلة من العالم الخامس
This was going to be Superman, or it wasn't worth my time or their money.
بل انها ستكون مثل سلسلة "سوبر مان" والا فانها لا تستحق ضياع وقتي ولا مالهم
So from day one, the people involved in the project,
لذا من اليوم الاول ، الأشخاص الذين أنخرطو في المشروع هم :
bottom left is Fabian Nicieza,
ترون في الاسفل على الجهة اليسرى " فابيان نيسيزا "
writer for X-Men and Power Rangers.
وهو كاتب سلسلة " رجال اكس " و " باور راينجر "
Next to him is Dan Panosian,
وعلى جانبه " دان بانوسيان "
one of the character creators for the modern-day X-Men.
وهو احد اهم راسمي شخصيات " رجال اكس "
Top right is Stuart Moore, a writer for Iron Man.
انهم كتاب كبار .. و .. ستارت مور كاتب سلسلة " الرجل الحديدي "
Next to him is John McCrea, who was an inker for Spiderman.
وعلى جانبه جون ما كريبا .. وهو رسام و ملون لسلسلة الرجل العنكبوت
And we entered Western consciousness
وقد استطعنا ان ندخل للذهن الغربي
with a tagline: "Next Ramadan, the world will have new heroes,"
بعبارة " في شهر رمضان المقبل .. سيكون لدى العالم ابطال جدد "
back in 2005.
كان هذا في عام 2005
Now I went to Dubai, to an Arab Thought Foundation Conference,
وقد ذهبت الى دبي .. الى مؤتمر لمؤسسة الفكر العربي
and I was waiting by the coffee for the right journalist.
وكنت هنالك انتظر بالقرب من القهوة لأجد الصحفي المناسب
Didn't have a product, but had energy.
وكنت لا املك المنتج بعد ... ولكن لدي الطاقة والفكرة
And I found somebody from The New York Times,
وقد وجدت احد الصحفين من صحيفة أوقات نيو يورك
and I cornered him, and I pitched him.
وقد حصرته في الزاوية .. ومن شرحت ملخصي
And I think I scared him -- (Laughter)
و اعتقد انني اخفته حينها -- ( ضحك)
because he basically promised me --
لانه وعدني حينها
we had no product -- but he said, "We'll give you a paragraph in the arts section
رغم انه لم نكن نملك المنتج بعد ولكنه قال سنعطيكم مقالا في قسم الفنون ..
if you'll just go away."
على شرط أن ترحل عني
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I said, "Great." So I called him up a few weeks afterward.
قلت له رائع . .ثم هاتفته بعد عدة اسابيع من ذلك اللقاء
I said, "Hi, Hesa." And he said, "Hi." I said, "Happy New Year."
وقلت له " اهلا حسن " قال اهلا .. قلت " عام سعيد "
He said, "Thank you. We had a baby." I said, "Congratulations."
قال " شكرا .. لقد رزقت بطفل " قلت له مبروك
Like I care, right?
وكأنني اهتم لهذا ، مثلا
"So when's the article coming out?"
ثم سألته " متى ستظهر المقالة "
He said, "Naif, Islam and cartoon?
قال لي " نايف .. الاسلام والكرتون "
That's not timely.
الوقت غير مناسب الان
You know, maybe next week, next month, next year, but, you know, it'll come out."
ربما الاسبوع القادم .. او الشهر المقبل .. انت تعلم بحسب الاوضاع في الاروقة الثقافية
So a few days after that, what happens?
ولكن بعد عدة ايام ماذا حدث ؟
What happens is the world erupts in the Danish cartoon controversy.
حدثت مشكلة الرسوم الكرتونية المسيئة في الدنمارك
I became timely.
فجأة أصبحت في وقتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So flurry of phone calls and emails from The New York Times.
لذا هاتفته وارسلت له عدة رسائل الكترونية الى مكتبه في النيويورك تايمز
Next thing you knew, there's a full page covering us positively,
والذي حصل لاحقا اننا حصلنا على صفحة الغلاف
January 22nd, 2006,
في ال22 من يناير من عام 2006
which changed our lives forever,
والذي غير حياتنا للابد
because anybody Googling Islam and cartoon or Islam and comic,
حيث أن اي احد كان يقوقل للبحث عن الإسلام والرسوم الكرتونية
guess what they got; they got me.
كان يحصل على ماذا برأيكم ؟ علي أنا ..!! :)
And The 99 were like superheroes
والـ 99 كانو مثل الأبطال الخارقين
kind of flying out of what was happening around the world.
حيث كانو يطيرون خارج كل ما كان يحصل في العالم
And that led to all kinds of things,
وهذا الامر قاد لكل أنواع الأشياء
from being in curricula in universities and schools to --
من كونها أصبحت في المناهج التعليمية في المدارس والجامعات
one of my favorite pictures I have from South Asia,
إلى احدى الصور المفضلة لدي من جنوب اسيا
it was a couple of men with long beards
حيث يظهر رجلين ملتحيين
and a lot of girls wearing the hijab -- it looked like a school.
وحولها الكثير من الاناث يرتدين الحجاب .. يبدو انها مدرسة
The good news is they're all holding copies of The 99, smiling,
والخبر الجيد انهن كانوا يحملن صورا للابطال ال99 ويبتسمون
and they found me to sign the picture.
وكانوا يردون ان اوقع لهم على تلك الصور
The bad news is they were all photocopies, so we didn't make a dime in revenue.
ولكن الخبر السيء ان تلك الصور كانت مزورة جميعها .. اي لم نحصل على اي ريع من ورائها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We've been able to license The 99 comic books
وقد تمكنا من ترخيص السلسلة القصصية للـ 99
into eight languages so far --
في 8 لغات حتى الآن
Chinese, Indonesian, Hindi, Urdu, Turkish.
الصينية والاندونيسية والهندية والاوردو والتركية
Opened a theme park through a license in Kuwait a year and a half ago
وقد افتتحنا مدينة ملاهي في الكويت منذ عام ونصف
called The 99 Village Theme Park --
تسمى مدينة ملاهي الـ 99 بطلا
300,000 square feet, 20 rides, all with our characters:
على مساحة 300,000 قدم مربع .. تحوي 20 لعبة لابطالنا
a couple back-to-school licenses in Spain and Turkey.
كذلك ادوات القرطاسية للرجوع للمدرسة في تركيا واسبانيا
But the biggest thing we've done to date, which is just amazing,
واكبر شيء قمنا به حتى يومنا هذا وهو امرٌ رائع
is that we've done a 26-episode animated series,
هو اننا انتجنا 26 حلقة رسوم كرتون
which is done for global audiences:
لكي تنشر للجمهور حول العالم
in fact, we're already going to be in the U.S. and Turkey, we know.
وفي الحقيقة قد بدأت بعض الدول في عرضها مثل تركيا والولايات المتحدة الامريكية
It's 3D CGI, which is going to be very high-quality,
انها رسوم مولدة بواسطة الحاسوب وثلاثية الابعاد .. اي ذات دقة وجودة عالية
written in Hollywood by the writers behind Ben 10
وقد كتبت بواسطة كتاب من هوليود هم نفسهم الذين كتبوا سلسلة " بين 10 "
and Spiderman and Star Wars: Clone Wars.
والرجل العنكوبت و حرب النجوم وحرب المستعمرات
In this clip I'm about to show you, which has never been seen in the public before,
وسوف اريكم في هذا المشهد والذي لم يعرض من قبل
there is a struggle.
صراع بين شخصيتين
Two of the characters, Jabbar, the one with the muscles,
الاولى هي جبار صاحب العضلات
and Noora, the one that can use light,
والثانية هي نورا التي تستخدم الضوء
are actually wearing the cookie-cutter fascist gray uniform
ولكنهم يرتدون الزي الموحد الرمادي لرجل الشر
because they're being manipulated.
لانه تم خداعهم
They don't know, OK,
وهم لا يعلمون ذلك
and they're trying to get another member of The 99 to join them.
وهم يحاولون جذب احد الابطال ال99 لكي ينضم اليهم
So there's a struggle within the team.
لذا هنالك صراع بين الفريق
So if we can get the lights ...
هلا خفضتم قليلا من الاضاءة
["The 99"]
ال99 بطلاً
Jabbar: Dana, I can't see where to grab hold.
جبار : دانا لا استطيع ان أرى اين امسك بيدي
I need more light.
احتاج مزيدا من الضوء
What's happening?
مالذي يحدث
Dana: There's too much darkness.
دانا : هنالك الكثير من الظلمة
Rughal: There must be something we can do.
الدكتور رازيم : لا بد أن هنالك شيء يمكننا القيام به ؟
Man: I won't send any more commandos in
الرئيس : لن ارسل اي من قواتنا الخاصة مرة اخرى الى هناك
until I know it's safe.
حتى يصبح الامن مستدباً
Dr. Razem: It's time to go, Miklos.
راجال : حان وقت هروبنا يا ميكلوس
Miklos: Must download file contents.
ميكلوس : علي تنزيل الملف اولا
I can't forget auntie.
لا يمكنني ان انسى عمتي
Jabbar: Dana, I can't do this without you.
جبار : لا يمكنني القيام بذلك دونك
Dana: But I can't help.
دانا : ولكني لا استطيع المساعدة
Jabbar: You can,
جبار : بلى تستطيعين
even if you don't believe in yourself right now.
ان كنت لا تؤمنين بنفسك الآن
I believe in you.
فأنا أؤمن بك
You are Noora the Light.
انت نورا .. انت الضوء
Dana: No.
دانا : لا
I don't deserve it. I don't deserve anything.
انا لا استحق هذه القوة ..انا لا استحق اي شيء
Jabbar: Then what about the rest of us?
جبار : ماذا عنا .. ماذا عن بقيتنا
Don't we deserve to be saved? Don't I?
الا نستحق ان يتم انقاذنا .. ماذا عني ؟
Now, tell me which way to go.
الان اخبرني .. اي طريق الذي يجب ان نتبعه
Dana: That way.
دانا : هذا هو
Alarm: Threat imminent.
إنذار .. خطر محدق
Jabbar: Aaaahhh!
جبار : آآآآه
Miklos: Stay away from me.
ميكولوس : ابتعد عني
Jabbar: We're here to help you.
جبار : نحن هنا لمساعدتك
Dr. Razem: Don't listen to them.
راجال : لا تستمع اليهم
Dana: Miklos, that man is not your friend.
دانا : ميكولوس هذا الرجل ليس صديقك
Miklos: No. He gave me access,
ميكولوس : لقد اعطاني المعلومات .. وساعدني
and you want to reboot the [unclear]. No more [unclear].
وانتم تريدون التحكم بي . لا مزيد من التحكم
["The 99"]
ال99 بطلاً
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So "The 99" is technology; it's entertainment;
اذا قصة ال99 بطلا .. هي تكنولوجيا .. ترفيه
it's design.
وتصميم
But that's only half the story.
ولكن هذه هي نصف القصة فحسب
As the father of five sons,
وانا كأب لخمسة ابناء
I worry about who they're going to be using as role models.
قلق جدا للقدوات التي يعتمدها ابنائي
I worry because all around me, even within my extended family,
وانا قلق لاني ارى حولي .. وحتى بين افراد من اسرتي
I see religion being manipulated.
كيف يتم التلاعب بالدين
As a psychologist, I worry
وكباحث علم اجتماع انا قلق
for the world in general,
على العالم ككل
but worry about the perception of how people see themselves
وقلق اكثر عن كيفية نظر الافراد لذواتهم
in my part of the world.
في الجزء من العالم الذي اتيت منه
Now, I'm a clinical psychologist. I'm licensed in New York State.
وانا طبيب نفسي معالج .. مصرح له في مدينة نيو يورك
I trained at Bellevue Hospital Survivors of Political Torture Program,
وكنت اعالج في مشفى الناجين من معسكرات التعذيب السياسي في "باليفو"
and I heard one too many stories of people growing up
وقد سمعت قصص كثيرة عن اشخاص كبرو
to idolize their leadership,
ليميزوا زعمائهم
only to end up being tortured by their heroes.
لينتهى بهم المطاف ليعذبو من أبطالهم
And torture's a terrible enough thing as it is, but when it's done by your hero,
والتعذيب امرٌ مروع بحد ذاته .. ولكن ان تعذب على يد شخص كنت تعده بطلك
that just breaks you in so many ways.
فهذا يدمرك نفسياً على عده أصعده
I left Bellevue, went to business school and started this.
غادرت " باليفو " ودرست في كلية الاقتصاد ومن ثم بدأت هذا المشروع
Now, one of the things that I refer to
واحد الاشياء التي تجعلني
when I -- about the importance of this message --
متأكدا من اهمية هذه الرسالة
is that I gave a lecture at the medical school at Kuwait University,
هو انني كنت يوما اعطي محاضرة في جامعة الكويت
where I lecture on the biological basis of behavior,
وكنت اعطي محاضرة عن اساسيات التصرف لدى الانسان
and I gave the students two articles, one from The New York Times
فاعطيت للطلاب مقالتين واحدة من صحيفة نيويورك تايم
and one from New York magazine.
والاخرى من مجلة نيو يورك
And I took away the name of the writer, the name of the [unclear] -- everything was gone except the facts.
ولكني حذفت اسماء الكتاب والعناوين .. ولم يبقى سوى الحقائق
And the first one was about a group called The Party of God,
كانت الاولى تتحدث عن حزب يدعى حزب الإله
who wanted to ban Valentine's Day. Red was made illegal.
والذي خرج في عيد الحب .. حيث كان يمنع ارتداء اللون الاحمر تماما
Any boys and girls caught flirting
وكان هذا الحزب ان القى القبض على فتاة وشاب يتغازلان
would get married off immediately, okay.
يزوجهما على الفور ! تمام ..!!
The second one was about a woman complaining
والمقالة الثانية كانت عن امراة تشتكي
because three minivans with six bearded men pulled up
من ان 6 ملتحين ملثمين اختطفوها
and started interrogating her on the spot
واخذوا يستجوبوها
for talking to a man who wasn't related to her.
بسبب انها كانت تسير مع شاب لا يمت لها بقربى
And I asked the students in Kuwait where they thought these incidents took place.
وقد سألت الطلاب في الكويت .. اين تظنوا تلك الحادثتين وقعتا ؟
The first one, they said Saudi Arabia. There was no debate.
اجابوا الاولى في السعودية لامحالة
The second one, they were actually split
والثانية انقسم الطلاب
between Saudi and Afghanistan.
بين السعودية وافغانستان
What blew their mind was the first one took place in India,
والذي اذهلهم ان الاولى حدثت في الهند
it was the party of a Hindu God.
وكان ذلك الحزب هو حزب الاله الهندوسي
The second one took place in upstate New York.
والثانية حدثت في شمال مدينة نيوويرك
It was an Orthodox Jewish community.
في مجتمع يهودي محافظٌ جدا
But what breaks my heart and what's alarming
والذي آلمني اكثر .. وهزني
is that in those two interviews,
هو ان في هذه المقالتين
the people around, who were interviewed as well,
الأشخاص المجاورين الذي تمت مقابلتهم
refer to that behavior as Talibanization.
قالوا ان هذا التصرف هو تصرف " طالباني "
In other words, good Hindus and good Jews don't act this way.
اي في معنى آخر ان هؤلاء الهندوس او اليهود تصرفوا بهذه الشاكلة
This is Islam's influence on Hinduism and Judaism.
بسبب تأثير الاسلام السيء على الهندوسية او اليهودية
But what do the students in Kuwait say? They said it's us --
ولكن الاخطر هو ماقاله الطلبة في الكويت ؟ ان هؤلاء هم نحن
and this is dangerous.
وهذا خطير جدا
It's dangerous when a group self-identifies itself
أنه خطير عندما تعرف مجموعه نفسها
as extreme.
كمتطرفين
This is one of my sons, Rayan,
هذه صورة لولدي " ريان "
who's a Scooby Doo addict.
وهو يحب ان يتابع " كرتون سكوبي دو "
You can tell by the glasses there.
ويمكنكم التاكد من ذلك بسبب النظارات
He actually called me a meddling kid the other day.
لقد نعتني بالطفل الفضولي ذلك اليوم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I borrow a lesson that I learned from him.
ولكني تعلمت منه درسا قيما
Last summer when we were in our home in New York,
ففي الصيف الماضي عندما كنت في منزلي في نيو يورك
he was out in the yard playing in his playhouse. And I was in my office working,
كان يلعب في ملعبه في الفناء وكنت انا في مكتبي اعمل
and he came in, "Baba, I want you to come with me. I want my toy."
وقال لي " بابا .. اريدك ان تاتي معي ... اريدك ان تعلب معي "
"Yes, Rayan, just go away." He left his Scooby Doo in his house.
قلت " ريان .. اذهب " كان قد ترك لعبة سكوبي دو في ملعبه
I said, "Go away. I'm working. I'm busy."
قلت " اذهب اني اعمل .. انا مشغول "
And what Rayan did then
والذي قام به حينها
is he sat there, he tapped his foot on the floor, at three and a half,
انه وقف امامي وضرب قدمه على الارض كالثالثة و النصف
and he looked at me and he said, "Baba,
ونظر الي وقال " بابا
I want you to come with me to my office in my house.
اريدك ان تاتي الى مكتبي في منزل الالعاب خاصتي
I have work to do."
لدي عمل هناك لأجلك "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Rayan reframed the situation
لقد اعادة صياغة الموقف
and brought himself down to my level.
واستوعبني حينها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And with The 99, that is what we aim to do.
وعبر الـ 99 بطلا.. هذا ما نهدف إليه
You know, I think that there's a big parallel
كما تعرفون اعتقد ان هنالك فرق كبير بين مفهوم
between bending the crucifix out of shape
الصلب وبين مفهوم
and creating swastikas.
الصليب المعقوف النازي
And when I see pictures like this, of parents or uncles
وعندما ارى انا هذه الصور لآباء وأعمام
who think it's cute to have a little child
يظنون انه من اللطيف ان يكون ابنهم
holding a Koran and having a suicide bomber belt around them
حاملا للقران ولديه قنابل انتحارية حول خصره
to protest something,
ويستخدمونهم للتعبير عن رسالة ما ..
the hope is by linking enough positive things
وأملي هو ان استطيع ان اربط أمورا إيجابية أكثر
to the Koran,
بالقرآن
that one day we can move this child
حتى نتمكن في يوم من الأيام من تحويله
from being proud in the way they're proud there,
يوم ما فخورا بشيء ايجابي ..
to that.
إلى هذا
And I think --
واظن
I think The 99
ان الابطال الـ 99
can and will achieve its mission.
يمكنهم القيام بهذه المهمة
As an undergrad at Tufts University, we were giving away free falafel one day
في احدى الحفلات في جامعة " تفتوس" كنا نقدم الفلافل مجانا
and, you know, it was Middle East Day or something.
كما تعرفون كان يوما معد للشرق الاوسط او شيئا كهذا
And people came up and picked up
وقد جاء الناس وقد استمتعوا
the culturally resonant image of the falafel,
بالفلافل .. الدال على ثقافتنا
ate it and, you know, talked and left.
وقد تحدث البعض وغادر الاخر
And no two people could disagree about what the word free was
ولم يكن احد يختلف على معنى كلمة " free مجاني " و كلمة " falfel فلافل "
and what the word falafel was, behind us, "free falafel." You know.
وكانت هنالك لوحة اعلان بذلك خلفنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or so we thought,
حتى حصل
until a woman came rushing across the campus
ان جاءت فتاة تجري الينا عبر الحرم الجامعي
and dropped her bag on the floor, pointed up to the sign and said,
وقد رمت حقائبها في طريقها واشارت الى اللوحة وقالت
"Who's falafel?"
" من هو فلافل .. ولم القي القبض عليه " ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك) FREE = تعني تحرير ايضاً
True story.
قصة حقيقية
She was actually coming out of an Amnesty International meeting.
يبدو انها كانت خارجة من اجتماع منظمة العفو الدولية
Just today, D.C. Comics announced
وقد اعلنت اليوم منظمة الرسوم المتحركة في واشنطن
the cover of our upcoming crossover.
عن ان هنالك غلاف سوف يصدر قريبا
On that cover you see Batman, Superman
فيه الرجل الوطواط سوبر مان
and a fully-clothed Wonder Woman
والمراة الخارقة
with our Saudi member of The 99,
وبطلنا من السعودية من ابطال ال99
our Emirati member and our Libyan member.
والبطل الاماراتي والليبي
On April 26, 2010,
في ال26 من ابريل من عام 2010
President Barack Obama said that
وقد قال باراك اوباما
of all the initiatives since his now famous Cairo speech --
انه من بين جميع المبادرات التي حدثت بدءا من ذهابه الى القاهرة
in which he reached out to the Muslim world --
والتي خاطب بها العالم الاسلامي
the most innovative was that The 99 reach back out
فان المبادرة الاكثر إبداعاً كانت مبادرة الـ 99 بطلا
to the Justice League of America.
مع ابطال العدالة الامريكيين
We live in a world in which the most culturally innocuous symbols,
ونحن نعيش في عالم حيث معظم الرموز الثقافية
like the falafel, can be misunderstood because of baggage,
مثل الفلافل يتم فهمها بصورة سيئة
and where religion can be twisted
كما ان الاديان معظمها يتم تحريفها
and purposefully made where it's not supposed to be by others.
وتستخدم بصورة لم تأتي لاجلها
In a world like that,
وفي عالم كهذا
they'll always be a job for Superman and The 99.
سنكون دوما بحاجة الى " سوبر مان " و الابطال الـ 99
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)